[Music]
hey folks welcome back to the Dark Horse
livestream podcast Q&A section I have
put the potatoes in the oven for dinner
which I think technically means this is
a crossover a cooking show at this point
Wow
yeah how about the stakes the stakes are
they are marinating all right so we have
a lot of questions to get to and we will
not get to all of them we are going to
start with the questions that I
solicited on Twitter and then we will
get to as many of the super track
questions as we can
we've got a large influx so anyway
hopefully we'll get to your question if
you've asked one and if not our
apologies so the first question that I
wanted us to answer was from a Twitter
avatar Ari what do we think of
Madagascar's announced cure for the
Wuhan and nygma virus what Madagascar
has announced that they have found a
cure it is plant-based and they have
turned it into a tonic the plant is one
that is used to treat malaria but it is
not used in its raw form I'm not sure
exactly how it works but in any case
they have announced that they have a
tonic that they believe is effective
because they've cured a couple of people
and there are apparently many orders
from Africa before this tonic and I
think the president has famously drunk
some of this tonic on the president
Madagascar yes the president of
Madagascar has drunk this on video
demonstrating at least that it's not so
toxic that it would kill a president
outright all right what are we thinking
it well first thing yes yeah but let's
just say look first of all I'm rootin
for Madagascar we have spent a lot of
time in Madagascar it is a wonderful if
very frustrating place
as I would say desperately poor it's
almost always at the bottom of lists of
countries their guard to GDP and poverty
level and such it's yeah just
desperately desperately poor so let's
give the chances that this cure works a
strong and gamba gone by gamba yes Scala
Petra maybe yes exactly I'm now a tetra
maybe not all the gauzy French and
English all meaning probably not
probably not gonna work but here's the
thing I don't know what it means that
they've cured two people with this
because basically if you don't die of
kovat 19 you get better so you get
better less thirsty I guess if you've
had tonic on the other hand maybe
they've seen something and in fact I
should I should say we should not joke
so much about this I believe this arises
out of the pest or Institute which is a
place that you and I have actually spent
some time we've never been in but we've
spent some time in that part of Tana on
the capital city yep it's a real
Institute so anyway we're rooting for
you Madagascar it would be wonderful if
this worked and it would be great news
for the world and it would I don't know
establish Madagascar in a realm that it
is not typically thought of as the
leader in medical breakthroughs
so anyway that'd be great that said
highly doubtful that this is going to
work as I would say I at least am and
I'm sure you are of many of the hopeful
things that have been announced you know
I get several things a day where
somebody is announcing that the Cure is
just around the corner that this person
or that person has come up with it and
um believe it when we see it okay second
question is how does our concept of the
collective collective consciousness map
onto Jung's collect the collective
unconscious I should say that in English
how does our concept of collective
consciousness map onto Jung's collective
unconscious I would say it is almost the
opposite certainly when we formulated
the term Jung was on our mind but what
Jung means by the collective unconscious
is like an inherited kind of knowledge
that would exist within a lineage that
would not be a conscious thing right it
was easy
he's almost describing what we're
calling culture
yes I agree that's why I say it's the
opposite as it does function more like
culture now and I don't know enough
about Jung to be sure that it's it's a
perfect map there but it's at least more
related to our formulation of culture
than that of conscious yes in our schema
what he's talking about is very close to
what we call culture what we call
culture is the things transmitted from
one individual to another and edited by
selection consciousness is an active
exchange and parallel processing of
ideas so anyway it is his collective
unconscious is what we mean by culture
approximately and that's the inverse of
what we might mean by consciousness so
anyway great question thanks for asking
it all right super chat I will say that
there are a ton of good questions here
we won't get through all of them we
might begin doing I don't know every
ants podcast haven't gone back through
and just responding on our own time to
three or four the questions that we
never got to before yeah once we wished
we'd go in wish we gotten two and for
right now we've just tried to do a
really quick ranking based on sort of
you know dollar amount and first pass
like oh is that something interesting
there's a lot of kudos and gratitude
coming towards us for which we are
indeed grateful to you guys thank you
which is meta gratitude it's meta
gratitude big funny both I've learned
more from these live streams than I have
from my public education thank you
unfortunately the bar is low question
given the scientific lens both of you
view the world through where do you
stand on whether or not love is real
come on love is real I mean I I'm in
pain hearing that question because come
on I put it at the top because I thought
it was a I thought it was a fun good
question it's a great question but it
implies it implies that the person
asking it has not had an experience of
love so powerful that they are certain
of its existence I don't I don't think
we have to go there I think there is a
general understanding of those things
that science can describe as separate
from those things that many humans
recognize as real but science dismisses
as out
the realm of that which can be described
or explained by science and part of what
this evolutionary lens allows is an
integration of more of the parts the
subjective the qualitative aspects of
human experience where the scientific
understanding yes I would say for my
part these things are often more
tractable than science gives them credit
for that they're you know because it's
an emergent property and not one that is
easily seen with reductionism it tends
to be understood late too rather than
early and in the intervening period it
is often dismissed but I see nothing
troubling about the concept or any
hallmark that would suggest that it's a
metaphor in fact I think at this point
we can just simply say you can probably
see it in the brain scan your dog
definitely loves you and the explanation
for it is I don't think in any way
troubling it's it's honorable and it's
one of the greatest inventions that
evolution will ever have devised and I
guess I'll say to you that there were
when we were sort of blocking out what
was going to go in our book three of the
chapters in the middle are on sex and
gender and relationship and parenting
and on childhood and I was sort of
describing to you what I saw as as going
in each of these but I couldn't quite
find I knew that they all went together
but I couldn't quite find a through-line
and you said well the three lines
obvious the three line is love that's
that's why they're together there that's
what connects them and that's that is
how we get from from the beginning of
that whole section to the end and then I
believe your response was what's love
got to do with it what's love but a
secondhand emotion which I think is one
of the great lyrics of all time all
right yes anyway love's awesome Turner's
words in my mouth okay right there you
go okay next question
traditionally humans ate as much sugar
as possible to make it through winter
then shed the fat fluctuating fat stores
but it seems healthier to have a study
wait
when ought we follow ancestral footsteps
boy there's a lot in there
why don't we follow ancestral footsteps
is it self basically that question that
we asked throughout most of this book
that we are currently working on a
second draft of and which will be out in
about a year there is a there couple
things in the formulation of the
question though that are assumptions
that I'm not sure are right
traditionally humans they just when
sugar is possible to make it through
winter then shed the fat fluctuating fat
stories that's true in a temperate
climate but of course until estimates
vary but call it something between 100
and 200 thousand years ago all humans
were in relatively tropical I want to
put a seasonal here in in scare quotes
environments where there weren't there
were certainly seasonal fluctuations in
food availability but it wasn't so much
temperature variation and a putting on a
lot of weight at one season and losing a
lot of weight in another then the other
assumption here that I'm not sure about
it seems healthier to have a study
weight not at all convinced that that
isn't necessarily true I'm not sure it's
not true but I don't know that there's
evidence for that yeah I think they're
you know within bounds oh wow you know
100 pounds up and down is obviously not
healthy bad you know 10 pounds is
probably normal but but yeah I think
look we are off the end of the
evolutionary tape in some sense we have
taken our the genius of our ancestors
wisdom and turned it into a novel world
that is now making us sick it's making
us sick physically socially
psychologically and we have to figure
out what part of the wisdom still
applies and what part is no longer
relevant to us and that's really in some
sense the modern human condition
it is a reflection of an ancestral
conundrum that our our ancestors would
have faced many times but it is a
turbocharged version of it so anyway I
think you're on the right topic and
that question requires a highly
conscious deliberate response which is
going to involve many of us tapping into
each other's consciousness in order to
solve it next question
thoughts on h2o2 therapy thoughts
hydrogen peroxide in relation to kovat
19 issues you have thoughts on h2o -
therapy in relation to cope at 19 issues
you two have literally saved my sanity
thank you for the much neat honesty so
the question is about hydrogen peroxide
therapy which i think is also sometimes
called oxygen oxygen ation therapy i
know very i don't just a tiny bit about
it it's been it was bad it was brought
up as a possible cure for cancer the
idea being the cancer cell is often
existed in low oxygen environments and
it was imagined that they couldn't do as
well in high oxygen environments and so
if you add at h2o to hydrogen peroxide
to those environments unless increase
the level of oxygen you would cause the
cancer cells to thrive less well there
is a tiny bit of evidence I think that
supports the basic premise and a lot of
evidence that suggests actually no the
low oxygen environments in which cancer
cells are being found is neither causal
nor universal so that would seem to
debunk it as for therapy for co but 19
issues I would guess that there would be
similar concerns you know why why do we
imagine that we've got a low or a high
oxygen concern and when we see it are we
looking at a cause or an effect or a
correlation that's actually explained by
something else yeah I'm not in a very
different position from you I'm aware
that it exists but I don't know whether
to trust that it's highly valuable I
would say you want to be very careful
about the concentration that you use
hydrogen peroxide is one of these things
it's actually pretty safe at low
concentration because it's a molecule
that our ancestors encountered but at
higher concentrations it has caustic
effects that you don't want to inflict
on yourself so there's represent
concentration that you get in the brown
bottles is safe for most applications
but yeah breathing it being you know the
question
anyway proceed with caution yeah this
seems like a comment rather than a
question regarding confusing terms
gatekeeper linguistics also known as
spell casting so I think he's just
offerings Jim is offering up some some
terms that we can use to you know jargon
jargon that would appear to keep people
out is gatekeeper linguistics science
politics every rarefied field every
specialized field has this and then it's
the users will tend to bring out the
terms when they are least sure most
interested in confusing who they're
talking to and maybe they're not even
aware that that's what they're doing but
jargon gatekeeper linguistics is most
useful when you kind of want to put up
smoke and not have a lot of questions
come your way afterwards I have one fear
about this okay because nobody's ever
heard of gatekeeper linguistics it
functions as a kind of jargon
whereas jargon functions as a term of
art enough yeah okay so anyway don't
take it personally Jim I like where
you're going but maybe jargon is just
the thing people will recognize okay
although spell casting that has a nice
ring to it slightly big fam is there an
evolutionary argument for informing and
hypothesis that humankind's ability to
perform careful abstract thought is on
the decline due to being diluted by
population size that is nobody is as
dumb as all of us so to speak you know
there's there's something to the idea
that there will certainly be diminishing
returns as you plug more brains into
each other and so there's a point at
which those returns might not asymptote
but would actually be climbed because of
the cost of the confusion that would go
along with it on the other hand you also
get longer tails yeah you get longer
tails and the real question is you know
you don't have to plug into everybody
all the time
you can plug into whatever network is
paying the highest dividends for the
kind of question you're engaging so
anyway the danger you're talking about
is probably real if we just all do
exactly what we're doing on the internet
which is plug into some giant network
that doesn't have any coherence to it
but if we
edit down to productive subsets much as
possible and that should scale
indefinitely do you have thoughts on HIV
not being the real cause of AIDS I've
heard real doctors connect the fact that
HIV doesn't cause AIDS but it's actually
the drugs that they used to treat HIV
and in fluxes of toxins in the
environment particularly in Africa in
the 80s yeah I have some thoughts here
one Nobel laureate Kary Mullis back in
the early days he got his Nobel Prize
for PCR a very important technique in
biology and he pointed out that the
character the criteria that are used to
establish that a pathology is caused by
a pathogen were not met in the case of
HIV and so basically there were people
who had AIDS who didn't have detectable
virus and there were people who had the
virus who didn't have detectable AIDS
now the problem with this is that this
is a complex system this is not a
billiard table and acquired
immunodeficiency syndrome is a set of
things that unfolds when certain things
have happened to your immune system the
most obvious of them is attacked by HIV
which attacks killer T cells among other
things but anything that disrupts the
same upstream phenomenon will cause the
downstream set of symptoms so you
shouldn't even really expect that the
only thing that's gonna cause AIDS is
HIV because HIV basically attacks a
certain set of cells and anything else
that did that would cause the same
phenomenology likewise you might expect
that a certain number of people for
whatever reason have endogenous
resistance to HIV and therefore could
contract the virus and ever suffer from
the pathology so in essence what's wrong
is our expectation for a one-to-one
match between infection and pathology
that does not mean that there was not
some phenomenon circulating in Africa
that might have masqueraded as HIV in
light of the fact
people were searching for it but I don't
I don't know of any evidence and it
might be that I've just missed it but I
don't know of any evidence that that was
a widespread problem I would say in
general we know that HIV tends to cause
AIDS strongly tends to cause it and that
what we had was a pandemic arising out
of the spread of HIV good
the next is a recommendation for a book
that I'm at least not familiar with but
it sounds interesting the philosophy of
conspiracy theory is by map dentists
it's based on his PhD thesis in
philosophy and the writer says it could
be useful for language to help
distinguish warranted and unwarranted
conspiracy theories thanks for the devil
yep I would say conspiracy hypotheses
but yeah other than that yes next
question from Eko you said viruses are
free genes trying to get into the future
horizontally by moving between hosts
like genes space exploration mode is
exploration mode a universal and living
organisms and if so why so Ecco is
referring to a concept of mind called
Explorer modes and the basic idea is
that evolution has discovered ways to
enhance its discovery of adaptive States
so consciousness would be such a an
adaptation consciousness would allow us
to discover opportunities that we
wouldn't find absent consciousness I
can't say that Explorer modes will be
universal but I can say that the value
of Explorer modes is so high that
anytime one is available it will tend to
be discovered if given enough time so
yes I think viruses are evidencing
Explorer modes and I believe there will
be features of their behavior that
actually will cause pathology and that
we will thus be able to identify which
match the Explorer mode hypothesis but
that said the Devils in the details and
the trick is going to be coming up with
precise predictions that separate that
hypothesis from other things that would
explain pathologies
yeah let me also just say that two other
examples of Explorer modes that you
didn't just mention but which are
outside of the domains we've been
talking about are army ants in there
after they break bivouac and are looking
for new things to eat follow follow
these exploratory maps that you know
these landscapes that you can map and it
looks looks very much like the other
thing which is neurons in young brains
growing connections and then afterwards
having those connections selectively cut
as the brain sort of atrophy but mature
into the adult brain form yep
yeah so there's a question about
evolutionary explanation and other
things that match it I agree those are
actual examples of exploration and also
the way trees find the places in the
canopy that are empty and therefore have
disproportionate light yeah so there are
lots of things that look like this and
it's an important topic next question
does unconscious bias play a role with
respect to keeping our economy shut down
polling shows those more left-leaning
wanting to keep the economy shut down
knowing that an economic downturn hurts
Trump's chances for re-election so I
think there's I don't think the writer
means to suggest that left-leaning
people necessarily that the poll doesn't
show that left-leaning people wanted to
keep it shut down know that that will
hurt Trump's chances for election but
it's a hypothesis yes there is there
unconscious bias here well I believe
there's unconscious bias all over this
question I have to say I am not
convinced as much as I do think Trump
has clearly erred again and again with
respect to the response to the pandemic
it is not clear to me that in a matchup
with Joe Biden that this doesn't play to
his strengths because to the extent that
people are frightened and I think people
are frightened and will be you know more
frightened as winter returns
to the extent that they are they may be
looking for a strong person rather than
somebody who appears to be enfeebled by
encroaching dementia whether or not
that's actually taking place with Biden
it certainly appears to be and so anyway
I don't know how this plays out but I
must say I think it's time to pull the
emergency brake cable and find a
different path because whichever side
thinks they know how this plays out I
think they're wrong okay I'm not sure
that really addresses the question but I
guess when we started we you started
there and said yes unconscious bias is
clearly playing a role it's not clear
it's not clear maybe I would just finish
by saying it's not clear how much
conscious bias there is in this
direction but is there unconscious bias
in which people are playing to their
usual roles yes I think so okay next
question thank you does globalization
and social connectivity via technology
or consciousness derive a more
homogeneous culture across humankind
over time is cultural singularity
possible inevitable dangerous all other
questions all of the above but I think
we're stuck were caught between two
failure modes one is the homogeneous
failure mode and the other is the
inability to get along to comprehend
each other and to properly govern planet
Earth and I realize that I have a
dedicated group of antagonists so if I
say things like govern the earth they
imagine that I'm calling for some kind
of global dictatorship and the black
helicopters are about to descend because
not what I'm saying but we do have to
govern the earth because we are
employing processes that have global
scale consequences we have to govern it
right we are we are left with no choice
or we will destroy the place so to the
extent that that's necessary it may be
time for us to recognize that our
individuality is cultures is being
eroded whether we like it or not by all
sorts of phenomena and that doing this
in a conscious careful way is better
than just allowing the internet to do
to us and suffering the consequences of
not having proper governance that all
the scales that require it well just add
with regard to the last part of the
question is cultural singularity
possible comma inevitable comma
dangerous I fear that it's possible I
fear even more that it's inevitable and
I'm certain that it's dangerous very
well said
next question thoughts on a parent irony
with regard to Heights that's Jonathan
Heights contagion analogy of the rights
push to reopen that is risking infection
by mixing and the left's Bush to stay at
home that is accepting stagnation by
isolating question mark so this is I'm
not actually totally familiar I don't
remember
heights contagion analogy but I assume
from the question of this is bringing up
the you know well replicated result from
personality tests like the big five that
show the conservatives and more likely
have a very strong disgust response and
things like you know disgust and
response to disease and dirt or a
stronger response typically in people on
the right whereas people on the left
hand to have more openness and that's
just the clinical term openness to
experience and such and therefore to
some degree openness to disease and this
seems to be this seems to have flipped
those roles so there's a thoughts on the
apparent irony yes it has flipped the
roles there's actually a pretty
interesting paper that I don't know that
it adds much to this but it points out
the same apparent flip in the rolls
actually in heterodox Academy's site
which of course Jonathan height was one
of the founders of this week I could I
could probably find that and link to it
I'm not sure I have much more to say
right now about this though yeah I mean
it's interesting but again I think in
some sense we're all being led by the
nose and we would be wise to resist the
politicization which is causing the flip
and the irony that you're talking about
you know there's something just very
difficult to swallow about the fact that
yes the right is being inflamed by the
authoritarian nature of
the response to the pandemic they are to
the extent that they want to open back
up they're incorrect it's very dangerous
on the other hand there are features of
the lockdown that are so absurd that
it's easy to see how you could suspect
that the whole thing was garbage yep
so in any case we got a level up yeah
what's your take on the virus first
hypothesis stating that some viruses
predate cellular life could those have
fostered cell your life complexity is it
a chicken or egg dilemma
wishful attribution of intent question
mark this again from echo lots of
questions yeah
echo manages to get a lot into one
question I'd say the chicken and egg
question is easy so it can't be that the
question of could viruses proceed alive
I don't think the viruses that we have
could proceed the life that we have they
cannot be the origin but they've doesn't
require a host yes I mean it could be so
many steps down the trail that you can't
tell what they were but I think it's
there's no reason to suspect us the much
more parsimonious hypothesis is that
they have jettisoned cellular machinery
in order to be more effective at moving
horizontally and so actually the next
question also from echo sort of
continues this do you agree that stating
asteroids could carry virus remnants
capable of affecting earth life comes
back to stating that life forms similar
to ours have emerged before or elsewhere
in the universe Thanks so yes I do think
that those two things are the same thing
and they both seem totally implausible
away one thing is virus asteroids could
carry
virus remnants capable affecting earth
life and life form similar to ours have
emerged before or elsewhere in the
universe
so if if asteroids have shown up yep
with truly alien life and yes that is
consistent with you know the only the
only thing that's consistent with is
then life evolved elsewhere but the idea
that anything that evolved elsewhere is
actually capable and affecting us you
know if if life if life is evolved
elsewhere which it almost certainly has
the chances that it uses DNA as its
information molecule is basically zero
and you don't ever want to say it's zero
yeah but it's basically zero so there's
going to be some other information
molecule that is used to carry
information between generations but and
it may well have you know we might even
have nitrogenous bases but still not be
DNA or RNA and it might be silicon based
instead it might you know it may be any
number of things even if it was DNA or
RNA which is conceivable it would not
have the same code and so it wouldn't it
would be meaningless I actually think
that the much less likely thing is that
it was that the molecule was DNA oh I
think it's very unlikely but I'm saying
you could imagine that the chemical
structure would be analogous but even
that doesn't get you to infection
because the codon structure would be
wrong yeah I mean there's so many steps
to get to the molecule that looks
anything like DNA or RNA but yeah well I
agree with you 100% if it didn't involve
honor if it's not gonna be very
effective at infecting us it's not to
say you know in light of prion diseases
or something you couldn't get some sort
of you know phenomenon where some thing
caused a pathology that didn't interact
with our physiology and information
directly but it's so unlikely and you
know I mean this is the question is
specifically about viruses
yes but some other kind of pathogen that
could cause like a mechanical damage of
some sort or a toxin sure absolutely
yeah okay let's do let's try to get a
few more of these before we switch to
the other live Jack questions
super Jack questions your conversations
are insightful and have been an
important navigation aid for me thank
you
how do you square astonishing no how do
you square admonishing listeners to
subscribe like notify to help the
channel when merely driving algorithmic
support isn't the explicit intention of
those functions a requirement that we
fight in a game theoretic paradigm that
we did not invent so basically I would
say here's the thing you our viewers and
we have an aligned interest in creating
a substrate that this podcast can
function on this is very cheap to you
and it's cheap for us to ask it and to
the extent that people do it it creates
more content of a kind you want to see
so I don't feel too bad about it
who does it cost well it might cost
Google but I'm not too concerned okay
thoughts on the PCR testing used for
covin and how the creator of it said
that it should never be used for
identifying a germ and how the RNA RNA
steps being used to identify Kovan
aren't necessarily what live up to
Koch's postulates I wonder if the
creator of it is not referring to the
creator of PCR here and exactly
referring to Kary Mullis because you
already talked about a bit and I'm not
sure that he said should they were
abused for identifying a germ I think
that you actually already kind of
addressed this question
yeah insofar as I can understand exactly
what's being said do you want to add
anything there well just that Koch's
postulates are actually a predecessor of
the current standard for establishing a
causal relationship between a virus and
a disease and so we you know we did
address it earlier I'd be very surprised
if Kary Mullis or anybody else said it
could never be used to identify a germ
but if he did say that or anybody
credible said it I'd like to know what
their reasoning was yeah yeah what do
you think it's safe to run on an outdoor
trail if other runners passing by aren't
observing social distancing or wearing
masks signed apprehensive in Austin yeah
you know we've we've talked about this a
bit before and I think it's really a
question of decreasing your risks and
that you decrease them to zero and you
never leave the bubble that you've built
around yourself and you increase them
with every interaction that you have if
you're outside and you're running behind
other runners who aren't wearing masks
is likely dangerous you're in there the
plume of breath and they're exerting
selves and they're likely they're likely
releasing viral particles if they're
sick but passing them and you know maybe
even doing simple things like to some
degree working to blow out when you know
as you pass people as opposed to
inhaling I it's not fully safe but it's
safer than being in an enclosed space
with people in fact you know we we were
for the first time in an enclosed space
and we were actually got some tests
yesterday and you said to me while we're
waiting everyone's masked up but it's
just the three of us us and the nurse or
the PA in the room and you said I think
this is the most dangerous thing we've
done since lockdown you know right so
being outside being out in nature
running biking electric unicycling and
passing other people during the same
except for elective you know cycling
which alludes three of you do it's much
safer than a vast majority of things
that you might be doing yeah the
evidence really suggests this is very
hard to catch outdoors and on a slightly
related note as you pass the other
runner try to make it look effortless
you'll feel good so we're gonna do just
three more here and then we're gonna
switch to the superjet questions from
the current live stream hello doctors do
we have any idea when metacognition came
onto the scene for humans or our genus
etc can't wait for your book hopefully
it finds you in Vancouver Canada I'd
love it to find us in Vancouver Canada
it's a gorgeous city metacognition I
guess it depends a little bit on what
exactly is meant by metacognition to
understand you know what we describe as
consciousness and look at those species
that those other species that have some
form of consciousness you look at traits
like sociality and long developmental
periods which in humans we call
childhoods and multiple generations you
know three or more living together and
there's something else I'm forgetting
there oh you know by parental care of
course yeah
not inherently by parental care but like
social social parenting by at least more
than one member even if it's not by
parental care so the other great apes
have that all the other Apes have that
many other monkeys have that so what
else is included in metacognition the
right a theory of mind baboons have
theory of mind and they're not all that
closely related to us so there's there's
a lot of ways to look at it and we need
a little bit more specificity on what's
meant by metacognition yeah I think the
problem is that a you have to set a
threshold when you're ready to call it
metacognition and if you set the
threshold sufficiently low then it will
be super ancient if you threaten
yourself the threshold sufficiently high
to mirror what we have that you would
call metacognition then it's going to be
tied up with the evolution of language
which is still debated but almost
certainly goes back
let's see half a million years at least
language you said yeah yeah super super
very volatile see but you know again it
doesn't start instantaneously either so
there's you know proto-language and all
of that so anyway the question is really
tied up and where you set the threshold
and then we could take a course guess
but it probably wouldn't be too too
useful ok hi guys my question is do you
think it's the do you think it's that
the human race will slowly become less
naturally attractive due to artificial
ways of increasing one's attractiveness
like makeup and plastic surgery yeah yes
I mean yeah for for two reasons one it
takes the burden off of attractiveness
and so you you know you will over
evolutionary time potentially lose
something but then there's also this
question about creating an artificial
glut of a very prepackaged kind of
beauty which then suggests a kind of in
autumn tissa tea and then what becomes
beautiful is authenticity which is more
synonymous with ugliness or something so
it does get very confused I do think our
superficial obsessions are not healthy
and to the extent that they're being
amplified by multi-billion dollar
industries which seed our insecurities
in order to sell us stuff that it's it's
time to call it quits yeah that's it
it's a good question yeah final question
here do you know any Koba 19 study
telling us something more about what
happens to a person with asthma getting
kovat I love the show and both of you
guys oh we got it I think it's a radio
emoji so oh cool
might be it might be a battery I can't
tell from here in any case there is
definitely some irony there yeah boy I
have not seen anything specifically on
asthma we've we've looked at some of the
stuff on smoking you know looks like
smoking is not the comorbidity people
were expecting it to be it may not be
productive and may be productive it may
actually be a comorbidity it's confusing
yeah so I I suspect that asthma is not
as much of a risk factor as people would
think it should be for an acute
respiratory syndrome yeah but I don't I
don't actually have my fingers on any of
that you have to get I know do we have
right below I already did that one yeah
yeah so where is the Google there we go
okay do you have a link to your
probability diagram and/or supporting
evidence so I don't know if you can put
a link up or not I can find a way to do
it I'm a little concerned that you know
it's a demonstration of what such a
thing should look like but as I said I
don't want to be synonymous with that
belief because the whole point of doing
things by percentage is the hope that as
information emerges that one's position
is flexible anyway I've thought about
generating a blank one for people to
fill in their own percentages and
unfortunately the program I made it and
makes that a little harder than
could be but I will I will think about
either regenerating it or finding a way
to clear the percentage numbers and
giving a link to that for sure it's like
there aren't that many here so we may be
able to get back to a few more Oh some
more coming in now the next one just
seems to be not a question women and I
don't know what to make of this should I
just read this it just seems like a list
of words sure women in science like
rosalind Franklin DNA which is to say
she was the she's the unusually unnamed
co-discoverer of DNA along with Nobel
Laurel
Nobel recipients Watson Crick a
coronavirus of the type first identified
by dr. June Almeida in 1964 as for meth
one of the most beautiful women ever was
Hedy Lamarr actually I do remember that
that great women of mathematics account
has done a Hedy Lamarr thread in the
past which I also did not know until
then that she was a mathematician yes
amazing
I missed that we had not seen it but it
wasn't there a great Hedy Lamarr
documentary in the last several years no
so anyway it was something I wanted us
to see but I don't think we ended up
doing it you claim that creating
subjective experience was evolutions
simplest mechanism for allowing an
individual to compare two perspectives
what kind of mechanism could create
experience from scratch mechanism could
create experience from scratch it it
depends where you're asking the question
from line in other words let's just take
our visual cortex for a second our
visual cortex creates a representation
of the outside world and actually there
are elements of it that can be
understood from the outside in other
words basically it's like a computer
program that has declared an array of
variables that then mirrors the position
of objects in the world so it's a
physical representation of an outside
space that has an analogy to it I don't
find anything
troubling about the idea that you could
take neuronal wetware and you could
create a data structure that would allow
a representation of another person's
cognitive process to be represented
inside of it I think at some level the
more we learn about how the neuronal
processes actually function and the more
we understand about the complexities of
the brain the less this will seem like
something that is incompatible with what
we know of neurons I mean neuron each
individual neuron is interesting at a
level that should cause us to model it
distinctly from let's say a binary
computer but I believe we will get there
if we live long enough is there an
evolutionary basis for man flu maybe man
trade frequency for severity
maybe we're just babies so I think this
man flew in quotes in the original
question is a reference to the fact that
Koba 19 is killing more men than women
it's like fifty five forty five or even
sixty forty like it's it's quite
substantial and of course this isn't a
flu but it's like a flu in some ways but
you know what what might be the reason
behind it affecting men more severely
because actually let me say first I just
saw some numbers I think it might have
been Oregon actually just just the
Oregon numbers that show that actually a
larger number of women have tested
positive and it doesn't say what the
background testing rates are so it may
just be that women are getting tested
more and therefore more women are
getting they're being found to be more
of the people who are positive are women
as opposed to more of the people I
suppose the alternative I'm going to
confuse myself if I say it over again so
even though more women have just a
positive in Oregon than men
still more men have died than women so
even when the background expectation
should be well if it's if it's scaling
then more women should have died there
haven't so I don't I don't think this is
so surprising I think that there is a an
element of the way selection plays with
trade-offs that people have not spent
time thinking about so the analogy I
would use is tropical organisms tropical
organisms are spectacularly effective
competitors in general compared to their
temperate counterparts but they are much
less tolerant of variation in their
environment so they are simultaneously
strong competitively and fragile
physiologically that is to say they
require narrow tolerances to do the
amazing stuff they do men seem to suffer
from something analogous to this and
this is probably the result of the fact
that historically speaking there's been
an awful lot of polygyny in the human
species and that polygyny means that
sexual competition between men has been
very strong and that basically you
didn't want to be a male loser because a
male loser
I wouldn't reproduce so what that has
resulted in is selection for strong
competitive abilities in men which has
made them fragile over time in other
words in cultures where highly
successful men reproduce with multiple
women then winning the position of
successful man would be more
evolutionarily desirable and that would
cause the borrowing of future vitality
basically of longevity in the pursuit of
greater strength at peak and so men are
physically stronger but they age faster
and aging faster is a proxy for how
vulnerable you are to any pathogen
great I mean not great nice explanation
yeah I'm glad I live to see the end of
it
how does the next question how does the
pandemic simulation exercise parentheses
event 201 that took place shortly before
this outbreak influence your
understanding of how likely the virus is
to have been intentionally released I
know of
event 201 I know very little about it
particularly I would say that pandemic
simulation exercises should be expected
to be being run by governments
frequently given what has been
understood about the risk of pandemic
outbreaks for decades on to centuries at
this point that it would actually be
shocking if pandemic simulation
exercises weren't being run and just
like the idea that it was clearly the
fish market and with a seafood market in
wuhan that released this thing like that
there's there's something about putting
two things together that seem unlikely
we're actually if there was if this was
planned wouldn't they not have done a
pandemic simulation right before they
actually released a pandemic right yeah
I don't know I it's a rabbit hole I
haven't been down so I can't say very
much about whether this is gonna be
easily dismissed or it's one of these
things that seems crazy and is you know
more troubling when you get there but I
guess I should look into it uh would you
get dinesh d'souza to do his next
documentary about you Brett no yeah okay
good
shouldn't geopolitical stability be part
of the opening calculus for example of
bread baskets of the world US China
Brazil are disrupted scarcity leads to
hunger leads to war
now you're talking I mean yeah this is
it absolutely this is a major concern
and when we talk about the problem of
game theory at every scale in the way we
come off lockdown and face this the
point is unfortunately
you can't have a yahoo nation decide to
opt out of dealing with its pandemic and
not have the world suffer consequences
from the opt-out this is this is one of
the things that to the extent that you
look into the game theory is really
frightening is that we have to come to
terms or we are going to default to
lowest common denominator kind of
response so anyway yes I I have to say I
am concerned about something like a
destabilized world sliding into armed
conflict of a massive scale as one of
the possible end states here yep in
response to your answer on subjective
experience why call your new construct
consciousness if subjective experience
existed much earlier love you why call
it consciousness okay the problem is I
don't know how informed that question is
with respect to what we mean about
consciousness and why what I would say
is a great many people are interested in
the question of how consciousness arose
and how it functions we think they are
making an error and that the question is
not so difficult
if you define terms in a natural fashion
and so why wouldn't we be interested in
pointing out that this question which is
according to many intractable actually
has a relatively simple solution if
we're right then
that's a at least a big savings in terms
of time that might otherwise be wasted
pursuing you know a non-answer so I
don't know seems like the thing to do we
I believe we're defining terms naturally
and I hope that works and
we'll see good okay just going back to
the super check questions and comments
from the first the first live stream you
respect for your audience's made clear
by the level of personal integrity you
display many things for the gorgeously
articulate and balanced responses
wishing you all the best from Berlin
thank you must be really late where you
are you have there thanks for
referencing that science article love
you guys this clears a lot of things up
you're welcome with the prevalence of
politicized disingenuous and dishonest
news would you in the IDW be willing to
partner on a new trustworthy media
platform we get pitched this kind of
thing all the time and I would say what
we've got is unacceptable platforms that
obviously have a a desire to
infantilizes and to tell us what's true
do not have the perspective to do it
honorably or well and no we have no
ability to figure out where to go next
in other words if we somehow
collectively decided that the this the
censorious instincts of the major
platforms were unacceptable and there
was a place to go or that there was a
project that held the promise of doing
this that really wasn't going to just
take the efforts and squander them I
think we'd be all in you know I can't
speak for anybody else but because we
all need a platform that doesn't censor
us there would be a great deal of
enthusiasm but we've heard great
proposals and all of them suffer from
the question of what are the chances
that they are going to rise above all of
the other great proposals and so anyway
it's a lot of a lot of very little fish
and no ability to distinguish which ones
might have a potential yeah the short
answer is yes for sure but
separating the wheat from the chaff or
turns out to be more than a full-time
job and not one that either of us is
particularly good at yeah I think that
said I will say there is a project with
whom we have spent a great deal of time
talking about how the future might look
and maybe it's time to bring them on the
podcast and to talk to the world about
it okay I'm gonna pull one more from
here first does physical contact that is
handshakes and hugs have any
evolutionary benefit if so does this
benefit surpass the contagion risk of
such contact of course it has
evolutionary benefit touch is a big part
of how we communicate with one another
and it it conveys meaning and connection
in a way that words and even facial
expressions can't handshakes can proudly
drop off the list of things that we do
without really almost anyone losing too
much sleep over what's been lost to
nonverbal communication hugs you know in
Europe there are a lot of different ways
lot of different numbers of pecks on the
cheek that are used to introduce
yourself to each other these seem to be
very important to the cultures where
they are they are certainly high risk of
spreading certain kinds of disease hugs
are hugely wonderful and important so
you know is there an evolutionary
benefit yes
are some of those benefits worth
dropping for some of for some safety
reasons yes where Lyme don't know here's
a problem you're living in a world in
which instead of being in a small
population that's insulated from almost
all of the pathology is circulating in
other populations you're exposed to
almost all of them by virtue of
airplanes and other such things and so
yeah it's a terrible loss that normal
and contact is now dangerous at a level
that we have to think about these things
but I would ask you to consider how much
we are losing people are losing family
members who go to the hospital and
predictably die and nobody can be there
with the cost of what we are suffering
is so high that we really have to think
about how to stop it in its tracks and
how to prevent the maximum number of
people from getting it because the
horrors that occur in places where this
is happening to lots of people are
almost unimaginable indeed
next question many University grads
overvalue the normal distribution and
undervalue Black Swan events how do I
convince colleagues that outliers that
exist are important
wowthis that's a great an astute
question this is this is one of the
problems of having a little bit of
knowledge right that you get a little
bit of statistics and you see a bell
curve more theoretically known as a
normal distribution and you think and
you know maybe you even hear about
regression to the mean and and you think
everything is a normal distribution and
rare things because they're rare can't
be important you know obviously to lab
who you reference here with Black Swan
events has written a tremendous amount
on this his writing can be dense to put
it lightly how do you convince you you
can't you don't want to hand that bunch
of pull up books to colleagues and then
keep them as friends mostly how do you
do this in a simple conversation I think
it's gonna be so context dependent and
it's gonna be hard to give any sort of
rubric I would come at it a different
way okay I think the problem is we are
economically incentivized into this
wrong thinking
right now you reference people who have
college education and this may be one of
the ways that we are economically
incentivized to this wrong conclusion
but the basic point is if you are
properly concerned about Black Swan
events you are less competitively
effective under normal circumstances
because bell curves are common and that
means that these rare tail events which
are on a bell curve or a power-law
distribution whichever but the point is
if you play the game as if the Black
Swan events aren't going to happen you
may win the game for your entire life
and never see the Black Swan event so
you came out ahead for gambling on the
likely outcomes and only in the very
rare circumstance of the Black Swan does
the person's wisdom the person who was
trying to call your attention to the
danger show itself and they may not
survive to see their win much less are
they likely to be able to capitalize on
it since it's very hard to to time it so
in any case the point is look this is
actually a strategy that is unfolding
and those of us who get the Black Swan
problem are losing so I think pointing
out that in some sense this is a free
rider problem issue that a disbelief in
black swans is a competitive strategy
and it's an unkind one because it's
putting all of us in danger that's the
way to reach them so anyway try it out
I think accusing people who believe too
strongly normal distributions of being
Free Riders is going to be a tough sell
but I love it as an efficient well it
also it means that you won't be spending
so much time on the phone because you'll
start losing friends and they oh yeah
you do okay the way you opened up the
last live stream was great make America
civil again thank you okay what what a
react timewise we have time for one more
question
two minutes let's do one more question
all right all right is so there's one
here that's gonna be a much longer
answer about laying out the evidence
that makes you think a lab is the most
likely source although I would
say again just that you did a lot of
that in a few live streams ago and maybe
you'll come back to it I would just say
okay at some point I think it would be
worth going through the branches of the
diagram maybe there are branches that
aren't on there but I've tried to be
complete I probably need a garbage
branch for anything not contemplated
here but it would be worth explaining
the rationale for each of the
percentages so that people could
basically take on a model for what it is
that dictates why you would expect a
particular outcome and I should think
about whether or not there's a way to do
that that wouldn't bore a large fraction
the audience to tears okay and finally
is civilizations tendency to engage do
you read this one no is civilizations
tendency to engage in behaviors that are
productive in the short-term and
perilous in the long term a kind of
antagonistic pleiotropy does this mean
the society is doomed to senescence in
quotes or its analog yeah so one of
there's been a large number of people
who've participated in the patreon
discussions that I've been running now
for several years and one of the
longtime folks in the evolutionary
discussion posed the question is there a
cultural analog to senescence and I
thought it was so good that I made a
little video about it and basically my
point was you have fun your channel it's
on my channel basically civilization has
an absolute analog to senescence and
what we are living is the incoherence at
the end of civilizations life and
basically the short version is that
because things that are profitable early
and have costs late tend to accumulate
that those behaviors that are
economically productive but have
environmental consequences that are
dangerous tend to make people
politically powerful which tends to make
those properties irreversible and what
that means is that we are doing many
many things that are ultimately
destructive of civilization and this is
what senescence looks like so yes it's
more than an analogy we have the exact
phenomenon that causes a body to degrade
with age causing civilization to degrade
with age and if there's one thing you
should be most frightened of it's this a
civilization that cannot go in Reverse
when it has to is doomed
all right thanks Pam on that happy note
have we reached the end of the Q&A I
think we have all right well those are
some excellent questions we look forward
to the next one please don't forget to
like subscribe hit notify and if you
really love us comment it's just good
for you it's good for us and we don't
read them all but we do read many of
them all right be well stay safe
you